right
hi john thank you so much for making
time for this conversation i've been
really looking forward to it because
i've uh feel like i quite frequently
quote one particular sentence of yours
and
and it'd be wonderful to have uh that
explained a little deeper by you
um but i'll get to that later so thank
you so much for making time and
normally i start these conversations
with giving my my guest or my
conversation partner an opportunity to
tell a little bit about themselves
rather than me reading out a bio
um so you're one of
to my mind one of the leading
researchers in evolution and
complexity and i particularly like that
you come in from a complexity
angle to the study of evolution and so
yeah please introduce yourself and how
do you get into this
yeah well it's a it's
not a direct path that brought me here
um
and i don't know really what just where
to start but
probably the most significant event in
my life was when i
uh in grade 11 in school i did a there
was a new physics course
that emphasized problem solving uh an
open book approach and so on so
it emphasized uh you know
not right learning but bringing your
intelligence to physical issues
um and i i got 12 out of 20 in the first
test
and i'd never done so badly in science
before and it sort of completely rocked
me
um but i've been reading a book called
psycho cybernetics
which was a book about
the russian work on cybernetics
and the russians you know that was in
the 60s the russians were
extraordinarily advanced and i read
about algorithms for the first time
so the 1960s you could go a long way
through a library and never encountered
the word algorithm unlike today
and i heard that they were teaching
people algorithms
school students algorithms for problem
solving and they were doing far better
on problem solving tests so i thought
aha i've got to work out the algorithms
that can be used to solve these physics
problems
and i went went and interviewed the the
kids who did really well in class and um
and i i extracted their their algorithms
and then i examined my own thinking so i
turned attention inwards
to my own thinking compared it with
ideal algorithms
corrected my implicit algorithms and so
on
and after that the all sciences at
school were easy
um if it was like locking the unlocking
the door
to um uh intellectual understanding and
so on in science
um so that that was a major event in my
life and and
so that led to a long history of
self-examination self-correction
self-mastery uh remaking oneself
um and i remade myself to be
more and more intellectual um so it's
like the singularity where the ai
is so intelligent it can make a more
intelligent version of itself
and so on and bootstraps itself up into
the singularity
individuals can actually do that in my
experience so anyway
but my other great passion was fishing
so
uh i went to university doing uh
to become a marine biologist because i
could go fishing all the time
how logical is that you know and um
then i uh and then halfway through uni i
thought
god the barrier reefs you know just 500
miles north of here
i'm silly sitting in lectures you know
for nine months of the year i'll
i'll go uh so i went i went fishing and
i
soon earned enough money to buy my own
fishing boat and i was
mackerel fishing which is line fishing
it's an extraordinary way to make a
living
if you love fishing because you actually
catch them one by one
trolling around the reefs the reefs of
the
great barrier reef um but when the wind
blew
i used to you can't take your boat out
so i'd go to the library the library in
cairns
and i started reading the books at the
beginning of the dewey system double o
double oh one or whatever they are
and they're all the philosophy books so
at 18
when the wind blew and i couldn't took
my take my boat out i
was reading philosophy and i fell in
love with it and i knew then that
the life i'd foreseen which was having a
boat
rambling around the pacific around the
islands and so on
that wasn't going to be my life it was
going to be an intellectual life
a philosopher's life and soon after as i
read about evolution i realized that
i came to this intuition that a
comprehensive theory of evolution
must cover everything must cover all
change
must cover not just biology but you know
everything that preceded it and
everything after it
including you know comprehensive theory
of evolution must deal with politics
it must deal with global warming which
was an issue at the time but hardly
what it is now and how you organize
society to deal with issues like global
warming so
so that led me into evolution and uh the
but the
this is still early in my life but i'll
just i'm not gonna
it i won't go for every year like this
don't worry but
but the um uh but i
graduated went back to uni graduated got
my bachelor of science degree
and then i saw that in evolution science
which now i was in love with it was my
passion
in evolution science there was no room
for intellectuality
very little room for intelligence no
room for creativity no big picture
thinking
it was narrow what i would now call
analytical rational thinking mechanistic
thinking
um thinking that can only understand
those
those limited phenomena in the world
which
which happen to be able to be
approximated by mechanical models
when the great part of reality is far
too complex to be understood by
mechanical models that would have been
roughly around the time of
the selfish gene and richard dawkins
taking evolutionary signs onto a kind of
genetic reductionism that's right
well the turning point as i didn't learn
until many years later was that in
the early 40s um
the great evolutionary scientists of the
time actually had a meeting
and a series of meetings and they
decided that to become
a professional academic discipline they
had to narrow down
evolution evolutionary science to
mathematical models
the mechanical models uh and they
decided to use their
editor editorship of the key journals of
evolutionary journals of the era to
banish big picture thinking
even though most of these guys were big
picture thinkers
so they i say that evolutionary biology
put a gun to its head in the 1940s
and blew its brains out and we're still
in the shadow
of that event today so i decided that
you know i was vitally interested in
evolution i was vitally
interested in the big picture i was
vitally interested in intellectual
creativity
and therefore i should leave university
and not be an academic so everything
i've done
since then i've written a book uh
you know i've had about 14 i think now
papers big picture papers published in
international science journals
peer-reviewed science journals
but all that has been has been
uh not the way i earn my money
so i've i've been a trade union official
a government advisor
on wages policy and stuff like that
that's how i had my money then i retired
early
and and but all this has been done
uh where i had intellectual freedom you
in my experience you don't have
intellectual freedom in the academy
in the university you know you get
intellectual freedom by finding
an easy way to make the sufficient money
to live
happily on and raise a family and use
your spare time to
um to do the thinking
so your your affiliation with the free
university of brussels
is is just to give you an academic home
when you do need to have an affiliation
to publish a paper or
how did that link establish it well i
wrote my book evolutions arrow
which is a book largely about the
evolution of cooperation
and as my daughters pointed out to me
you know the irony is that
no one i never worked with anyone on my
my ideas it was
it was a totally solid
that's right so it was
yeah i never uh no one else read it i
never discussed the ideas with anyone or
any
any anything else so anyway when the
book came out and i circulated and so on
francis haligan who's the head of the
research group at the university of
brussels the evolution complexity and
cognition research group
and he developed principia cybernetica
which was
uh you know a site a
complex set of resources on complexity
thinking cybernetics and so on a major
achievement in the
90s so he he read the book
and knew that i had no affiliation and
said well come and join us and you can
yeah that can be your formal affiliation
and so on
so that gives me some some status within
academia but my main status within
academia is that
that i'm not part of academia yet i've
had these
despite that i've successfully had
significant papers published in
international peer-reviewed journals
so in a way you know i would say my
credentials are better than those who
simply got them by
passing exams and so on yeah
well i mean i i resonate in the sense
that that i i also always felt that
to really do the the research i wanted
to do um
i was better off outside of the normal
conventional academic system rather than
inside and
i mean i also started as a marine
biologist and then the
masters in holistic science and then a
phd in design
because i thought that design would give
me more freedom but then
um yeah the funding landscape was very
difficult at the time and
i i felt a lot more freedom um
reaching into academia rather than being
in it um
that's right well well academia i think
um
named tron chomsky said that the inside
of a modern major corporation
is the most totalitarian environment
that's ever existed in history
um but you know i would say that
corpora corporations are trumped by
academia
academic academic departments are feudal
you know they're designed by feudal
system
they're not designed to reward and
generate
creativity and innovative thinking and
so on
i mean i often lamented that and then i
i also trying to kind of sort of turn it
around and understand why
is this why has this pattern evolved
um it's it's very it takes a very
special kind of person if you're a
professor
and you've been slowly climbing on the
top of that heap of academia
and um you spent 30 40 years
based on a certain set of core ideas
doing your research publishing your
books publishing your paper
papers and then you get a bright young
student
publisher paper that completely derails
everything
that you've you've done and while on the
one hand
in theory that's how science goes in
human practice there it is
understandable that
that professors are then going who's
this young up start and they don't know
what they're doing and
and and so there's this suppression of
of new insight um because people find it
hard to admit that
they might have spent 30 years barking
up the wrong tree
and it is a you know a hierarchical
system where
that person who has his reputation to
protect
actually has happens to have the power
to suppress you
um so they can yeah it'll be
if they act in their own interests then
rather than that act as an invisible
hand that
you know produces good in the world
they're more likely to use it to
suppress you
and and then there's another layer not
that i want to go into critiquing
university in academia
in this conversation but but what i've
also noticed is that
those people who make political power
careers within the university system
as organizations are often not the
passionate researchers not
the people who are there to share with
their students their love for
for knowledge and inquiry but it's more
the the political beasts who want to get
the bigger paycheck
and um so i i often feel like in
universities the
four-let four letter gap floats to the
top
um that is is very often
unfortunately the case and then you get
the really brilliant researchers
being managed by not so brilliant and
slightly um
mistakenly motivated individuals that's
right the power
but but i would like to come come back
to the because you already mentioned
that word that that makes me
so interested in your take on evolution
i've
the word cooperation and that in your
work you you very clearly
are building models of an understanding
of evolution that
goes beyond this to my mind fallacy
that we um focus on
or have focus for far too long on
competition as the main driver
um of of evolution and don't understand
the the cooperative dynamics that
actually underlie in a much more
substantial way
um the the kind of competitive behaviors
that that float on the top um so i'd
love i'd love to hear
more about your take on the role of
cooperation
in in the evolutionary process right
because that yeah that is the main theme
of my work um so i suppose
you know the first general principle is
it's obvious in human affairs
that an organized group cooperative
group of humans
can beat an individual human at almost
any activity
so the you know the most competitive the
fittest
is going to be the cooperative so that
and it's easy to see why i mean a
cooperative group
uh has command over more resources uh
can act on a larger scale
uh can do many things that an isolated
individual
can't now that that general principle
applies at every level
so it applies at the molecular level
so you have uh an autopoetic or auto
catalytic set
of molecular processes that can
collectively reproduce themselves
and they will persist where individual
individuals that aren't part of an auto
catalytic set
won't persist so an auto catalytic set
because this
is highly related to autopilosis which i
know you've written and thought about
considerably an auto catalytic set is a
set of entities at any level where
every member of the set uh is catalyzed
or supported by at least one other
member of the set
so in in ecosystems you get these auto
catalytic
assemblages of species where species a
promotes the existence of b and b c and
and c d and then d promotes a
so once you get the closing of that
autocad catalytic system
then every member of it's pumped up uh
by by other members of the set and it
becomes a self-sustaining
auto poetic self-producing system
uh so that's that's the you know the
beginning of life
was the auto catalytic set of uh
catalysts
of protein catalysts that supported each
other this is linked to
prior genes work or
no it's no it's more stewart kaufman
uh yeah he was the
the key the um the first one to you know
write
extensively about this in his uh i think
his 1992 or three book
uh where he talks about all getting
order for free
and order for free is when the snake
hits its tail
so you've seen the the esoteric symbol
of the
the snake in his tail that's where the
set of catalysts
eat their own tail clo become a closed
system that pumps itself up
it's also you know the clearest example
of autopilosis
in the sense that it's self-producing
because everything is produced
by other members of that set and it
becomes a self-producing system
uh so you can get that at any level you
get in ecosystems
you can see it in human activities all
the time where
you know someone someone
in in economic systems where a
corporation assists cooperates with
another and then another and another and
and so on the cycles closed so you
so that happens at the level of
that's the first uh beginnings of life
at
the auto catalytic set of of proteins
but it's not yet living as i'll go into
a little bit more detail but
that's the first cooperative system that
you use it starts with cooperation
it doesn't start with a naked molecule a
naked gene
reproducing itself because the
probability of that arising is
you know is infinitesimal it's from the
system that reproduces through
cooperation
uh is far more likely to arise
as kaufman demonstrates um than
the naked self-replicating molecule
briefly and to get back to
the way you described it sort of m a b
c d and d d then gets help from a it's a
sort of linear chain but
isn't there also where the activities of
a b
c and d collectively change the
conditions in the environment
that then actually support all all of
them
um through the change in the environment
like
i'm just thinking about um the phases
in terms of planetary shifts where
we went from a um
atmosphere that was full of methane and
and co2 to more oxygen that was actually
generated by the
early like the cells in the early oceans
they then
allowed the possibility for life on land
to
to evolve um is that that's right so
so and that's that becomes a really
important issue in what i'll
what i'll discuss next but the
but yes there can be uh
you know other events that are created
by this auto permit except
that feed back and support its existence
um the problem becomes uh
that there is
there is nothing in the system that
that encourages that behavior or fixes
it or
pumps up that behavior it's
self-sustaining but it can easily just
break down as well and there's nothing
to bring it back into
alignment but but i'll i'll get into
that so
anyway so the critical thing is you get
self-reproducing
molecular processes and then you get
cooperative groups of self replica
of self-producing molecular processes to
to form the uh the first simple cells
and then you get groups of those simple
cells to form the
eukaryote cell uh and then you get
cooperative groups of cells to form
multicellular organisms
and then you get cooperative groups of
multicellular organisms to form animal
societies
of which humans are you know the example
most significant to us
and the human society started off as
little kin groups little family groups
uh and then you've got assemblages of
kin cooperatives of kin groups
to form bands then cooperatives of bands
to form tribes
and cooperative of tribes to form
agricultural societies
and eventually empires and then you've
got cooperatives to form nations nation
states
which are now the biggest organisms on
the planet
but that's interesting because the last
three stages you you named from
from my perspective um aren't entirely
like they've enabled a lot of amazing
things to happen in in human history
but but they're also to some extent
where we started
to uh like a step towards agriculture
that
stepped towards cities in the step
towards nation states
um we we actually started to create
more competitive structures um rather
than cooperative structures and
what comes well that's what that's what
drives the trajectory
so i mean the most startling thing in
this
trajectory of the evolution of life is
that the first cooperatives
were a micron less than a micron in
diameter
less than a million for the meter so
these first little protocells
you know invisible to the human eye
and successfully throughout that process
because you're getting
cooperation of of entities at one level
producing the
entities at a new level that then forms
cooperatives
you get this increase in scale so now we
have cooperatives
that can span a continent and
the next step's obvious you know if you
extrapolate that process it's
a cooperative on the scale of the planet
you know it's a planetary
society um
so the so that you know the trend the
trend is startling undeniable
clear but so what drive so what drives
it it's
what drives it is the cooperative
advantage
uh the advantages of cooperation of the
the new entities are formed out of
cooperatives then they start to form
cooperatives
and those cooperatives beat the isolated
entities
and then those cooperatives form new
and then they form cooperatives which
are more effective so
so it is a dance between cooperation and
competition yeah the sentence just
because it fits really well here the
sentence i
alluded to earlier that i um it's it's a
kind of um
not a direct quote but uh um based on
your work is
i love the way you've put it in one of
your papers that the
um i think it was the bio systems
paper on the evolution of cooperation in
you say evolution functions by a pattern
of diversification
and subsequent reintegration of that
diversity at higher levels of complexity
and comes the most important sentence
that
in most situations that jump to that new
level of organizations and higher levels
of complexity is a cooperative
a new form of cooperation and and
it's just from listening to you now i
haven't really clicked on that
the scale of it actually grows in each
step because
it's kind of starting with the indus
symbiosis theory of of two non-nu
um pro two prokaryotes okay
together and not digesting each other
completely but forming the first
proto-euka you carry a nucleated cell
and then at each step you you get larger
um cooperative organizations yeah
and that and the it actually yeah it
precedes the um
you know the margulies uh endosymbiosis
story as well in the sense that the
a cell is is so it's the auto catalytic
set of proteins
which are then governed by rna so the
first symbiosis
the first big cooperation was the rna
with the
metabolism the the the protein
uh now um
the so at every level the quad you get
the cooperatives formed
and then they compete with other they
breed diversity
diversify and compete with one another
and that that competition um
uh they can be
won by a larger scale cooperative
formed out of those cooperatives so
that's that's what drives the process
there's
there's um the formation of a
cooperative at a particular level
only solves the cooperation problem
and only exploits the advantages of
cooperation
at that level at that scale there are
further advantages that haven't been
exploited
and those advantages can only be
exploited by a yet larger scale
cooperative
and then those cooperatives compete uh
and that leaves uh unexploited
advantages of cooperation
um at a higher level formed of
cooperatives of those cooperatives
um so the now and the important thing is
is that
at any point in time through
evolutionary history
the largest scale cooperatives that
exist compete with one another
and from their point of view that
competition is destructive
um so when you get uh
uh tribes you know there never was a
period
uh you know the green and spiral
dynamics terms fantasy
the tribal societies were harmony it was
a time of like the garden of eden where
they're harmonious and so on
so they're the highest level
cooperatives of a particular level
are harmonious and cooperative within
them
but they compete so australian
aborigines for example i remember being
startled many years ago to
to be told that it's very common in in
aboriginal languages and there are many
throughout australia
that whatever the language the term that
they use to describe their neighboring
tribes often is translated best
translated as
sub-human or animal
and that of course legitimates you
killing them
and you have to because you know imagine
in australia the
aborigines come to australia they expand
fill the available volumes so to speak
they form tribes and so on
um you're going to get overpopulation
any any
tribe is continually under threat of
incursion by the surrounding tribes as
their population
grows so they within tribes
you have cooperation and harmony between
tribes
you have war um
and you know vicious war until you get
larger scale cooperatives of multiple
tribes
um so that on that larger scale you get
cooperation within it but you still get
competition
uh between destructive competition
between those
cooperatives of tribes and other
cooperative tribes and and clearly
that's you know so when you
you refer to um these recent steps
uh you know the emergence of nation
states uh
the destructive comp the destructive uh
competition between nation
states the unexploited potential for
cooperation between nation states
is driving you know the destruction of
civilization
uh it's highly likely that human
civilization will end
this century and the cause of that will
be
you know the unexploited benefits of
cooperation between nation states in
other words the
destructive competition between nation
states within nation states you can get
some
semblance of of um
uh you know dealing with problems that
that can be housed within the nation
state the biggest problems that threaten
the world now
are the impacts of nation states um
that extend beyond the borders of any
one nation state
uh and therefore the there's nothing
there's no unilateral action
that a nation state can take that will
deal with that particular problem
i often wonder whether the entire
concept of a nation state is actually
part of a sort of maladaptive
evolutionary pathway that
um because it's it's very linked to
um the divorce
of the human pattern from
the pattern that sustains life when you
look at it in terms of a
planetary process my sense is that
one of the blind spots of most
evolutionary theory is that we still
look with like you're obviously not a
genetic
reductionist in in the dawkins type
terms of
looking at the um competition between
selfish genes and all that
but but we still tend to look at um
evolution in a kind of speciesist way
and which is valid and useful and gives
us lots of
insights but i feel like there's a
there's a complementary on the other
side of that that really needs to look
at life as a planetary process
and the whole notion which is a
relatively recent
socio-political notion of a nation-state
even if you just look at the borders of
nation states drawn by the rulers of
rulers
um in a in a kind of colonialism
competitive process um
we we need to rematch
our human patterns to the biophysical
patterns
of the wider planetary life process and
that's why in my work i work a lot with
bioregionalism
as as one attempt like watersheds just
as the initial
rough pattern because at least a
watershed is a biophysical pattern
not a sociopolitical pattern but then of
course in our culture we we've
we've divorced from the biological
evolution through
technological and mimetic evolution that
that we
now have a huge proportion of humanity
many of the people sitting in those
academic ivory towers we talked about
earlier
that honestly believe that culture and
nature can be separated that somehow
where we could develop technologies that
would make us independent of our
nature as biological beings which which
i think is a bit deluded
well yeah that that brings up
probably the most critically important
point that
comes out of you know the evolutionary
worldview that i've
that i've been developing and that is
that
at lower levels when you had very large
populations
of cooperatives competing so the
multicellular organisms
you know and you have
you know population sizes in the
millions or whatever
then you have you have competition
between those
cooperatives and the most effective ones
survive
and you get feedback loops from the
environment and so on that wipe out
those that destroy their local
environment
uh and so on so the in effect you know
one way of saying it is is that natural
selection disciplines
the behavior of those you know
multicellular cooperatives
the problem we've got in the world today
is that there are
under i think 200 nation states
there is not a you know great turnover
of nation states nation states don't
you know have a thousand offspring that
then compete and
and and the most effective nation states
survive and so on
so you don't have that big discipline in
that big feedback loop or anything else
so so what you're pointing to this
mismatch
between nation states and their
effective
uh persistence in an environment in a
way that
is sustainable um you point to that
mismatch
yes if natural selection was operating
on
populations of a million competing
nation states
it would sort all that out and only the
the nation states that weren't
mismatched would survive
but that's not happening there are only
200 nation states
it gets far worse when you take the next
step
because the next step is a global system
there is no population of global systems
there's only one
so the you cannot have this continual
experimentation
which is the only way nature's ever
discovered
um to uh
choose between complex systems uh
and when i say the only way nature's
discovered i'm including the human mind
in that which is
clearly part of nature uh the human mind
is incapable
uh of understanding complexity in
general
and uh designing and
well designing is the wrong word anyway
but growing
complex systems that have particular
effects that are predictable and
controllable and so on
um so the only way
in in one of your more recent papers you
you
what did you call it i
i found it here hold on a minute um
consequence capture yeah and and
um that kind of fitted well for me or
even
also what you just said would again in
my mind say
if we want to create a global
cooperative
entity that coordinates
fitting human patterns back into the
biophysical patterns of the life support
system
where part of emerge from and are
dependent on
then um we need to create
our patterns in a scale linked way from
from local to regional to global
um but most of the patterns need to be
at the regional scale
so the feedback is quick enough and and
you could easily then see how different
cooperatives
of different bioregions the ones that
would have patterns that regenerate and
restore
and support the ecosystems health of the
region they're in
will out compete the ones that
draw too much on on their um yeah
by region so so it's it's almost like
we've
we've jumped to nation
state scale without paying attention
with losing like in the in the move
towards globalization
we sort of lost the multi-level
redundancies
at local and regional level that
actually builds
in terms of patterning of life as a
planetary process
builds the um resilience into the system
that we can continue evolving
yeah consequence capture has to follow
the principle of subsidiarity
which is you have you have the um
you deal with issues at the most local
level possible
now some issues can't be dealt with
except at the global level
um and basically the definition of a of
an issue that can't be
dealt with except at the global level is
an issue that has
impacts beyond the borders of nation
states
so it's only through action across
nation states
that you can implement consequence
capture
in other words deal effectively with
those sorts of issues and global warming
is the classic one you know if america
produces a stack of carbon dioxide
there's no
action that any other state can take
that can insulate it from
those actions of america so it needs you
need a system that reaches across nation
states
and coordinates their behavior and
implements consequence capture
so that's a good segue into constant
capture consequence capture is the
principle
that i would argue applies at every
level
to produce cooperatives that then evolve
effectively
as a coherent whole and evolving
effectively as a coherent whole
means that they develop agency plans
uh actions on the outside world and so
on
that's what happens to all these
cooperatives that emerge at each step
in the evolution of life on earth so
consequence capture is simply that you
they have to be mechanisms in place that
ensure
that the actions at every level within a
cooperative organization
uh the actions of any entity at any
level um
feedback or reflect back onto the entity
the consequences of the effects of its
actions on the entity as a whole
so to give a more concrete example
what it would mean for human beings if
if we lived in societies that
implemented consequence capture uh that
ensured that
individuals captured the consequences of
their actions on the whole
it would mean that if they acted in any
in any way that
you know had a detrimental impact on the
environment then
they there would be feedback mechanisms
which deterred them from doing that
similarly if they acted in ways that had
positive effects for the
cooperative of humanity as a whole
they'd be rewarded for doing it
so one one simple example is that
in a properly organized planetary system
you and i would be wealthy
because we would capture the
consequences of our actions on the
whole um because because what we do is
not profitable
you know in fact we have to sacrifice
our opportunity to
you know to achieve the the things that
society says of the supreme goals
that is to make lots of money we have to
we have to give that up
we're deterred p far from being
uh capturing the consequences of of
trying to design
systems that benefit humanity as a whole
you know it costs us to do so we have to
forego other opportunities
um the another example i give is that
so so what i generally do when i talk to
people overseas
is i apologize
for rupert murdoch
[Laughter]
who is the most successful australian in
conventional terms ever you know
his world impact is massive
uh but it's a totally detrimental impact
i mean
he uh yeah he's playing a significant
role
in in the destruction of the planet
through his manipulation of politics and
so on through his
media empire but but the example i give
is that if
if a young rupert murdoch was in a
um a society where consequence
capture applied then and he was plotting
out his life
path you know in order to be uh he
wanted to be a billionaire
let's assume he's just the same as he is
now in terms of his end motivation
then instead of saying oh you know the
way to make my billion is to uh
have a media empire and manipulate
politics and everything else uh
in a world where constant constant
capture applies then it will be
might be far more profitable to uh
reduce child mortality in africa
introduce schemes that
that you know promoted sustainable
agriculture in
africa or whatever so consequence
capture
um is is
a world in which uh
when individuals within that system look
at
how they can advance their interests
they find they can
best do it by doing things that benefit
the planet as a whole
whether they have any intention at all
whether they're a good person
at all whether they're spiritually
developed at all it doesn't matter
um so let's take the example of the
cells in your body
you're a galaxy of um you know 10
trillion or so cells
those cells individual cells uh
spend their lives pursuing their own
little cellular interests
uh you know which is taking some what
they what's food to them and expelling
some waste and
reproducing or whatever they don't know
you
they're not they don't care about you
they
don't care whether you live or die or
whatever they just are following out
their own little
cellular interests yet they're embedded
in this system that rewards them
whenever their
cellular interests lead to the the
common
interest and that orchestrates them
to behave in ways that produce your
speech
you know your intelligence your thinking
your action and so on
so this global super organism um
would um would have consequence capture
so we don't have to wait for everyone to
be
uh systems thinkers to understand what
there is to do
because you know if if that's what we
rely if that's what we have to rely on
we're finished human civilization is
gone
which is just briefly um because that
example is quite interesting to me in
the sense that
of course of those cells um only a
subset
are actually human cells and
many many of that ecosystem walking
ecosystem that is talking
to you from majorca all the way down to
australia
um is actually a set of cells in my
in my body on my body that help again
without knowing
me they help what i refer to as me
have all these complex um thoughts and
and actions
and um so how do we
create such consequence capture
quickly enough with without like because
for me
i i agree with you with regard we can't
wait
to have everybody at that sort of
enlightened self-interest level
of understanding the complexity that i
actually
by serving life i serve myself and the
most enlightened way
um to serve myself is is to
create conditions conducive to life
everywhere um
and to some extent i mean
you mentioned aboriginal culture and in
general indigenous culture is not
necessarily
living this what what is often portrayed
as
as this this sort of um golden past
where
everything was was fine but but they
even if they were competing tribe
against tribe um
the common
understanding that
they were in our modern language
emerging properties of the land
that um they walked on that that they
belonged to the land rather than the
land belonging to them
that ultimately um
as they were doing their hunter-gatherer
migrations in a certain regions that
they that today we would maybe call
their territory
um they were stewards
of the biological processes their myths
and storytelling
and their dances all their practices
were ways of communicating to the next
generation
um where not to go in certain times of
the breeding season in order to
get to keep that species um able to
reproduce
they might have closed the clothes that
in the spirits are there doing whatever
and so you don't go there because it's
taboo
um but if we do the research
yeah so the point i'd make is no they
didn't clothe it
in taboos and so on
they believe the taboos and they pass
the taboos on
uh and the tribes that had taboos
that were produced harmony with their
environment
those tribes persisted so the key point
here is
a very important distinction in
knowledge is between
procedural knowledge and declarative
knowledge
and procedural knowledge is the
knowledge you have about
when you ride a bicycle
and people basically don't know what
they're doing when they ride a bicycle
but they do it and it works and the
bicycle off they go
swimming um people don't know what it is
that enables them to actually swim when
they learn how to swim
that's it's procedural knowledge that
they've learned
it's not declarative knowledge so
declarative knowledge is when
when you can put into words a model
of what riding a bike involves
and interestingly enough most physical
activities are so complex
that procedure we're not very good at
putting into procedural knowledge but
but the emergence of sports science
is the emergence of the translation of
procedural knowledge into declarative
knowledge
so the the tribes had procedural
they you couldn't sit down with a tribal
member and say you know what is it that
you do
um that ensures that you have
uh sustainable relationships with your
environment
they wouldn't that language would mean
absolutely not those concepts would mean
absolutely nothing to them
what they would say is is that oh well
we um you know
we believe that in you know if event a
occurs that's because we've angered some
god over here and that causes
to do something else and blah blah blah
blah
and us coming along with our procedural
knowledge and our science could say oh
if you look at how all that adds up that
ensures that they don't
um over exploit you know particular
resources
um so and this you know as i said
my ideas are you know clash with
post-modernist thought
and green and sphero dynamics thought uh
because they want to
you know hold up indigenous people has
been able to teach us a lot
no teaching is declarative knowledge and
they don't have the declarative
knowledge
they have the procedural knowledge the
best
books that i've that make this clear
is one of the the few anthropologists
who was also a
cybernetician and a systems thinker and
it wasn't gregory bateson but it was
someone who followed in gregory
bateson's footsteps gregory bateson you
know is one of the handful of genuine
systems thinkers the world seen most
systems thinkers
at most systems thinking
is constituted by mechanical models of
systems
not by so that's not systems thinking
gregory bateson didn't have that his
the reason why his you know his stuff is
still red and everything the reason why
it impacts on people
even though hardly anyone understands
what he said is because intuitively deep
down
if you if you've got an open mind you
know
that there's something going on here
that is wisdom or whatever
anyway the the guy i did is a guy called
rapper paw
um and uh and he i think his first book
was pigs for ancestors
and there he traces through
these rituals and um uh
processes involving pigs um
that in certain circumstances and only
those circumstances where they actually
slaughter pigs and so on
and he shows how wise
the effects of those were but how none
of the participants none of the tribal
members in these new guinea tribes
um you know understood it as wise action
they unders they
it was because of you know myths and
beliefs and taboos
but isn't that maybe precisely the less
like like i mean
maybe that's my own tinge of of the
green meme speaking here but i
i i sense that there is a both and that
it
in terms of um it's not a going back
to indigenous wisdom and saying oh now
we've
we've got it wrong with modernity we
should now put our tools down and and
just
humbly say we're stupid and go to um the
remaining
ancestral wisdom keepers on the on the
planet and say
teachers and tell us um a
my question there is how many of them
are truly unadulterated wisdom carriers
of the ancients
or the ancestral knowledge and to what
extent have they all
been also affected by modernity to
to the point that they're not really
speaking from that yeah i'm saying that
i'm saying that's that's not the big
problem the big problem is
the is that the wisdom was never in
declarative knowledge yeah exactly
but you keep going yeah because i'm
interested my question there
is it's just what you were just speaking
to
that example that rappapo tells about um
that particular tribe um is similar to
what you were saying is how how do we
create
without having to get everybody up to um
why can't you think like gregory bateson
and we all should and then we would be a
wiser species
um creating frameworks
that allow for that consequence capture
to actually be
inbuilt into our human societies
yeah and that's that's the challenge so
so just
to continue along with the bad news the
really bad news that
um but bad news is
in my view essential to understand if
we're to move the other side of it
so the future will not involve a return
to the past
it'll be going through the bad news to
the other side
through hierarchy it'll be and through
markets
so markets will be very important but
they won't be like our current markets
and hierarchy will be very important
but anyway coming to this so the new
guinea tribes and they're
a fantastic laboratory that's why you
know margaret mead and gregory bateson
and these guys
jared diamond and someone cut their
teeth as anthropologists
in new guinea tribes because there are
there are
you know there are thousands upon
thousands of them a great population of
tribes
and the and hidden and separated by
valleys
and therefore they're wonderful
experiments for watching in effect
the processes of mutation you know like
new taboos arising new
myths arising and so on and seen how
they were selected
you know by the environment and produced
this procedural knowledge
that isn't declarative knowledge so it
was in effect natural selection large
populations competing and so on
but throughout the whole evolution of
evolutionary history of life on earth
that's driven this spreading
widening of of cooperation on increasing
increasing higher scale but when you get
to the
situation where you've got uh it's
increased on scale
so much that you only have 200 of these
cooperative entities to cover the whole
planet
uh then that mechanism of that
automatically
without declarative knowledge without
insight without intelligence
produced behavior that was
extraordinarily
intelligent extraordinarily systemically
intelligent
like all these processes in your body
that digest
food moves stuff around your body and
everything
the human mind is totally incapable of
understanding
how that happens it's just a fantasy to
think that we are anywhere near
understanding
all that was produced by trial and error
and selection
all produced by automatic evolutionary
processes
so um this is what it amounts to
evolution on a planet and similar things
happen on
you know billions of planets i can
guarantee it
um evolution on a planet proceeds up to
a certain point
unconsciously through selection
experimentation and so on then when it
gets to the stage we're at
the processes that drove it
unconsciously
fail and the only way it can proceed
from here on in
uh is consciously
intentionally through declarative
knowledge
so that's that's really bad news
the good news is that it means that
humanity has enormous work to do on this
planet
it means individuals you know once you
see this bigger game
that you're embedded in uh
and a human life's like this you you
start off in a family game
you know where you're a member of a
little family and then you go to school
and you're in the school game and then
you graduate and so on and
you're entering wider scale systems
uh and unless you commit suicide to
those
you know the future potentials you
you realize you're in a wider game and a
wider game and you
join in that game positively and you
make a contribution
to it and while you believe in that game
you it gives you
meaning and purpose in your life well
the biggest game we're in the greatest
game of all the evolutionary game
and we're so lucky that there's a role
for us
in that game an intentional role we're
not like
you know the the process that's led up
to now where it all happens blindly
through trial and error and selection we
actually have to
our role is to to understand where it
needs to go
which is global consequence capture
until you have global consequence
capture you have global warming
global environmental degradation the
threat of nuclear war
which is the threat of nuclear war is
extraordinary
i mean pakistan and india have
nuclear weapons donald trump and i hate
to be disparaging about red-headed
people but
he's not he's everything about him
category he's a fake redhead
but but he has yeah he has new nuclear
weapons
so there again something that
no individual nation state can insulate
itself
against other countries handling of
nuclear weapons
no individual nation state can insulate
itself unilaterally against
the production of global environmental
degradation
from carbon dioxide emissions or many
other
actions of other nation states
only a global system can implement
consequence capture
um and of course then
so the question is how do you introduce
how do you this magical
process of consequence capture that
results in
individual entities not having any
concern for the whole
but finding that when they when they
pursue their own little individual
interests it benefits it's all aligned
with the interests of the hull that
benefits the whole
how do you introduce this magical
consequence capture
and that's very bad news for the green
meme
because it's all done by power and
hierarchy
so this this is where we autopolisis
isn't enough so
returning to the uh autocatalytic set
the autopoetic
system of of proteins
you know to take the simple one and i
it's a network not a
a circle but the reason why i describe
it as a circle
is because that's the only way
declarative knowledge can transmit it
between us
easily um so the circle abcda
um you know pumps itself up
uh is autopoetic it can it
produces itself through time
but it's not life because it's not very
evolvable at all so
so for to explore the possibilities of
cooperative organization
then any uh
catalyst that can contribute
to the uh to the little auto poetic part
uh has to be integratable into that
organization
so if uh hg
zed you know happened to be able to
really give the
the system a boost but they're not
catalyzed by any
any member of that uh existing auto
catalytic system
then that boost can never be realized
um and just to make a leap uh
just briefly because that to me speaks
exactly to the the the bit that i'm so
searching for which is
the um not coming
from the division
of life into
individuals and species which clearly is
one way of seeing and gives lots of
insights
but coming from the opposite coming from
the
the allen rayner calls it inclusionality
or
from from true um dynamic
wholeness where all of it is actually
a evolving um yeah
unity might be like but i'll i'll get to
that so
shoot me if i don't you know sort of
wave and accuse me of being a child and
a fraud if i
forget it so bring me back onto the
track but but this builds to that so
so you've got the little autocoder
catalytic cycle
and there's a whole lot of
potentialities that it can't integrate
because there are all these other
chemicals
that could contribute to the
functionality of that little cycle
but can't be but can't because they're
not catalyzed
um by the integratable into the cycle
because they're not catalyzed
so what was the solution so that that's
like the metabolism in the protocell
let's
that's like your cells without dna and
rna
pure autopilosis pure autocatalysis
so what introduced consequence
consequence captures when any other
chemical
that can benefit the whole captures the
benefits of that so it does get
supported
anything that would harm the whole
consequence capture means it gets
punished for
say a free rider that extracts benefit
from the cycle
but gives nothing in return consequence
capture means it's harmed by doing that
so what introduces that consequence
capture and the answer is
you you know at the beginning of life
you had the autopoetic
system of um
catalytic proteins rna came along
rna was the governor of the cell
rna was the powerful entity that could
act across the cell
and had the power to catalyze h so h
was the one who could really benefit the
little cycle
but couldn't didn't have consequence
capture so rna
can support h and therefore enable the
system of which now rna is
the governing part enable that system to
um
to incorporate h and be self-sustaining
with h
and and you can extrapolate that i mean
that's the whole story of the emergence
of life it's
a powerful entity that can introduce
consequence capture within a metabolism
um the
then you so that's that's the prokaryote
then the story of you know the that's
really fascinating to me the
the metaphors used uh in biology are
clearly a result of people's
developmental levels and where they are
in the spiral
so the best thinkers in biology um
uh are generally the ones who are common
not not the real system series but the
the best thinkers
you know are green and so they see it as
collaboration as um the equal partners
you know the prokaryotes getting
together and
and producing a whole no
no what what happened was that the the
big cell
who has the power it's its dna rna has
the power over
everything that goes on in that cell it
introduces consequence capture
the cell engulfs the little the small
bacteria
and then the rna dna the governor of the
that cell then manipulates
that bacteria that became mitochondria
in its own interests
it enslaves it it introduces consequence
capture
so when so the mitochondria the
internalized
small bacteria still do what
you know still pursue their own
interests but you've got this
consequence capture implemented by the
the rna dna the genetic apparatus
that ensures that the only way it can
pursue its interests is if it
if as if it serves the whole and
so it is each of these steps so it
so but isn't it i mean i i hear you and
i agree with you
kind of somehow the the enslaving bit
um was maybe a strong metaphor that that
i'm not quite sure whether
i would um on the right because
because it isn't it goes both ways um
like it the mitochondria actually needs
the context
of that larger cell in order to um
continue
as a mitochondria so so um
it's it's a mutualism rather than an
enslavement to some extent well that's
well that's what that's what certain
yeah most biologists
the bigger picture ones you know the
green ones because the mechanical ones
you know don't have this no but the the
bigger picture ones
uh they see it as yeah mutualism
um but there is clearly a power
relationship there
yeah i mean that i did one of the things
that i found
very useful because you bring in spiral
dynamics in that framing with the green
meme regularly is
one of the issues that that ken wilbur
kind of identified of like the
hierarchy being such a trigger for
people that are kind of
arrested in the green meme and the
distinction between
dominator hierarchies and um
evolutionary
hierarchies is is very important there
that that
you need that structure of hierarchical
systems but
but they they can actually be enabling
to all parts of the system rather than
the the top dominates the bottom which
is
my understanding that's right so so a
smart dominator
creates conditions in which uh
you know the good source self-organizers
bottom up
[Music]
so so the the the smart dominator
uh you know farms
farms the uh the auto catalytic set of
proteins if it's an rna dominator
or it's the large cell with little cells
within it it farms
but farming is domination so that so
what's happening on a farm
the really good farmer if he's really
smart
the way to really get his farm going is
to have uh to promote cooperation
between
[Music]
different species that he's farming
but it is a power relationship so modern
corporations
uh you know 100 years ago scientific
uh management used to be uh
taylor yeah it was embodied by taylorism
taylorism is how mcdonald's restaurants
work so
every every worker
in the dominator who's dominated by the
dominated hierarchy has set
tasks to carry out set procedures and
they
follow them out and they together make
up a machine
but modern organizations that each
in a competitive environment where they
have to be successful
um they have to be creative and so on so
the so the
the they've nonetheless still got a
dominator you know the manager of the
ceo
the board whatever but they're far more
subtle
they're far more like rna and and
dna and the genetic apparatus and so on
they create conditions where
uh you know with increased freedom uh
and so on the market
uh markets are extraordinarily creative
now is it necessary
to and just in terms of semantics to use
to still use the word dominator there
because if it is a growth hierarchy that
actually benefits
and all scales of the system
um the what you call the dominator just
being
like that the power of those
higher ranking elements
in the hierarchy and
depends on the consequence capture and
the healthy functioning
that's right at the lower level so so it
they're not
all powerful they they're only there
as as long as what they're doing is
enabling
the whole to continue to grow grow and
evolve and
and that's where in in my framing it
it's just
and and i feel like that's where we can
make peace with the green meme
um in a in a kind of healthy expression
of meme and
uh the green meme and move beyond it
yeah is is
um to to just be sensitive around
the language use and and see them more
as enablers rather than
dominators even if they have a certain
power over
yeah they will well they do have power
over
so that's and that's an essential part
of it so
so if if in translating it into dealing
with green people
um you know you lose sight of the fact
that there is a power relationship
then you lose sight of an element that's
absolutely essential
so to introduce consequence capture
in the on the planet you need
global governance that is powerful but
in the absence of competition between
you know all these global
systems competing and therefore being
disciplined by the need to be effective
and not be exploitative and you know
global governance that
that is exploitative will produce a far
less effective super organism than one
which
which governs and promotes cooperation
and so on
but but if but if it if you leave out
the the element of power then it doesn't
work
it all becomes uh you can't get
consequence capture
you is you need power you need
constraint but then what you do
is you need to constrain in the absence
of competition to constrain the
you know the governance um you need
you need systems to then constrain that
governance
so arguably uh if you look at the
history of human societies
a key evolutionary event in the
evolution of human societies was the
magna carta
and then then
the introduction of democracy because
the magna carta was a form of constraint
on the king to make sure that the king
governed in the interests of the whole
or more so he
is massively overblown um but
but the story of the magna carta but
in but it was a constraining of the king
uh democracy
is a is an attempt to constrain
uh government so that it has to act in
the interest of the whole
so so when you lose natural selection
and competition as a way of
constraining the cooperatives you need
the cooperatives to include mechanisms
that constrain its governance
to ensure that it's not abused but it
still is
it still is all about power and but when
i listen to you like it it
does to some extent i mean language use
is slightly slightly
different than than i fully resonate
with but but
what you're explaining is um very
linked like for example earlier when you
said that
that in order to have consequences
capture you need subsidiarity
that is fully aligned with where where
my
and i'm i'm not saying i've got anything
i'm just i'm searching
for yeah yes but but increasingly i'm
i'm realizing if
if on this planet we want to i call it
redesign the human impact on
on earth within the lifetime of the
generations alive today
um but being fully aware that design is
never
a kind of um fully
prediction and control based type of
design it doesn't like it's
dancing it's a dancing with the
complexity um
and and like brian goodwin was one of my
mentors in understanding complexity
said that with the insights from
complexity
the the the purpose of science of the
scientific
enterprise changed from increased
prediction and control
to appropriate participation and and i
find that
that's very useful and if we if we want
to create
a global system that has this
consequence capture built into it then
we actually need to
redesign governance to enable
subsidiarity at the local and regional
scale
but we need to have a very clear
system of disincentivization of any of
the bioregions
um like basically i think the healing
of our relationship with the planet so
we can continue
as one of the species on this planet
would would be we need to
everywhere regenerate healthy ecosystems
functions
um we need to increase bioproductivity
and heat heal
heal the soils bring back the forests
heal the water
waterways both um marine
and and freshwater systems and
to my mind that can only be done at the
local and bioregional scale
and the global entity of coordination
would be as long as you people in your
region can demonstrate
the regenerative impact on your
bioregions you get the benefit of the
global
um system because we're not going to
fall back into producing everything
at the local level or the by regional
level yeah um
but but the minute you you fall out of
that you you
then then the the sort of
um stick rather than the carrot is
consonants yeah yeah yeah and you
you both say you have a hierarchy of so
i don't use the term dominator
i'm not that provocative so i call it
just management
and you know and you can have you know
idiot
mechanistic management or you can have
extremely effective
subtle management that hardly seems to
be there
you know like the the uh
the chinese wisdom tradition says that
the way to govern a country
is the same way you cook a fish you cook
it lightly
um and the uh as if it's not there
that's that's you know so there's a lot
of wisdom in how to actually govern and
how to introduce consequence capture
but but broadly speaking there's a
hierarchy of governance
uh and the and consequence capture is
uh kept to the lowest level that is
where it's effective
um and every level of power
has to be constrained uh to ensure
so this consequence capture has to apply
to those processes that implement
governance and consequence capture
and then there it has to apply more than
anywhere else because
there's power there so you absolutely
have to constrain it otherwise it's
potential for doing harm is far greater
so you
you have to subject it to constraints uh
and design these processes where the
only way the governors
can act uh effectively for themselves
is to govern in the interests of the
whole
um at whatever level they're at but
whether it's you know at a lower level
or
at a higher scale but yeah just just to
to sort of have
now probably have the most difficult um
issue of all raised so so
the big insight i had that led to my
views was
you know i can remember to this day it
was in my fam in the family room of my
house in canberra
where i was living at the time
and i had this and it is a vision
it's a vision of equivalence and the
vision was that
the cell managed by the genetic
apparatus
introducing consequence capture for the
cell
was equivalent to the globe
uh managed by humanity
introducing consequence capture for the
globe
now uh so
the planet probably the the end point
of evolution for the planet is
equivalent to
the way a cell is organized um
where that gets sort of difficult um
for probably most people is that so i'm
not talking about
consequence capture only for human
society
yeah yeah so coming back to you
it's your fundamental thing that you've
been
trying to raise and emphasize throughout
this and i've sort of
moved off into other things but i
intended to come back to it it's
yeah i mean humanity the only
in any way the only
to believe that humanity is somehow
separate or separable or imaginable
as separable uh to everything else
in the whole universe in fact is to have
a mental illness
so it's only the analytical rational
philosophers who are manifestations in
my view of a mental illness
who can think you know can think oh yeah
what
humanity is separate so so how should we
behave and what are the consequences of
that i mean it's just crazy
so so consequence capture has to apply
to the whole system so
so the the emergent
uh you know next step in the evolution
of life on this planet
is not human society it's it's the
global super organism uh
with humanity in relation to the other
living processes and the physical
processes
the you know biogeochemical cycles on
the planet and everything else
the relationship of humanity to them is
the same
as the relationship of you know the
genetic apparatus
to the cell so uh so consequence capture
has to apply to the whole thing but then
then the really bad news comes in so
i'll just get that off my chest
because because then if you step back
and look at the whole shebang
from the beginning of living processes
cooperatives
of smaller than a millionth of a meter
across
and gradually increasing in scale and
christening scale until you have
a cooperative for the whole planet
um
if you look back at that whole process
and say what the hell is it
what it what it is what is analogous to
is an egg
so and i take the old chicken egg so so
the chicken egg begins
with you know a fertilized egg
a cell infinitesimal on the scale of the
the egg and then that reproduces and
forms structures and
so on and so forth using up the yolk
and the yolk is the coal and
uh the coal and fuel
and you've got to use up the yolk
otherwise you'd never get you know if
there's a revolution
within an egg you know when you got a
few thousand cells and they said
sit there and they say shit we're using
up this yolk
you know that's not sustainable we'll uh
we'll run out of yolk and we'll all die
we'll be finished
to an extent you know we need to use our
yoke
but we you need it to build the next
bill to the next level where we don't
need the yogurt
right is it yeah you said that the
fossil fuels were
like the starter engine on on spaceship
earth that we
we needed it to get to that next level
of making the whole thing
all right oh well isn't that wonderful
so
yeah i use the yolk analogy but it's
exactly the same
so i like yours better because it's
biological rather than mechanistic
and you can imagine these smart cells
waking up and saying fuck we're you know
we're eating our way out of house and
home here
just very briefly please come back to
this
i just wanted to make this analogy from
what you said earlier and what very much
relates to this is that
um if you look at buzz holling's work on
um
resilience uh and and
maintaining health in ecological systems
and then
taking that to socioecological systems
very often
resilience gets a bad word because of
course we've we've now seen that part of
the the problem that we've had is that
the old system we built is incredibly
resilient and keeps bouncing back
but this the distinction between three
levels of resilience of the
the kind of um persistence level
so in the face of this disruption i stay
the same
and then then if that disruption gets
too strong and i get
temporarily pushed out of balance
then there's an adaptive part of
resilience where you
where you can adapt a little bit and
bounce back to
more or less status quo those are the
two
two levels of resilience that you
observe also in ecosystems
but when you when you take the jump to
socioecological systems where you
include
our human affairs as we're obviously
part of
ecosystems everywhere now you bring
that important dimension of foresight of
awareness of what's coming into the
system and that's where
you can have transformative resilience
or
the evolutionary jump um that actually
necessitates our human awareness
of what is going on in the system
in order to say okay we've we've
almost used up all the yolk it had all
sorts of terrible
side effects um we're hitting
a window let's not argue whether it's 10
or 15 or 20 years that we've got left
to avoid cataclysmic climate change it
might be less
um but with that foresight we can now
begin to
establish that um global consequence
capture which which to me
that's why i'm hopeful that this notion
of planetary health is
slowly gaining traction this is to come
back to the inside that
the only way that we can continue our
journey is actually if we
um create a growth hierarchy system that
enables where our human actions enable
all of
all of life to flourish um yeah well
that's
that's where i said i've got a difficult
point to get over there
um which i'll quickly move into so um
but yeah i agree totally so so
um consequence capture is essential
uh so you know
a lot of people who write about this
stuff and what humanity has
to do uh you know in order to survive
and we must do this and we must have the
we must change our values and we must do
this and blah blah blah
and of course um the
you know you and i agreeing we must do
something has almost zero impact on the
world
uh because there is no consequence
capture there is no you need consequence
capture
um to motivate incentivize
and evoke the action which constitutes
the adaptation and consequence and
the adaptation and taking into account
of future eventualities
[Music]
so organisms at lower levels uh
they don't have foresight like us but
they do act
um to avoid future detrimental events
and they do so because natural selection
will produce that in an organism
natural selection ensures consequence
capture
and and therefore gets them to adapt
for what stafford beer who was a great
cybernetician
he talked about adaptation for the
inside now
which is uh organizing your metabolism
and adaptation for the outside future
and the outside future is the
cooperative
adapting in relation to its outside
environment and for future events
and that's what the global system that
can only now be built intentionally
not through the accumulation of
procedural knowledge
the global system has to have built into
it
uh systems that enable to adapt for its
outside future
and that outside future will include you
know linking up with
uh other eggs planetary eggs that hatch
elsewhere uh and other planetary
organisms this is fascinating because
because it is i mean staffordshire
viable systems model again
like basically speaks to the need for
that foresight and that contextualizing
um system within the the viable system
um and as you were speaking i was
sort of taking what you were saying to
the the logical consequence which is
one way of enabling us to evolve
that kind of consequence capture within
our planetary system would be the
corroboration of of of the the current
i mean i would agree with you you kind
of alluded to that earlier
and that it's more parsimonious to
assume that life has evolved in
different ways on many many planets
in in
[Music]
the universe that we're currently not
aware of
than to assume that we're the only one
place
in this vast system millions of suns
with gazillions of planets orbiting
around those suns
that that have had some form of um life
evolve but but
are you saying that in order to make
that jump we actually
need to contextualize ourselves in a
cosmic evolutionary context
and um we need to use our foresight
to see that there is you know
this living context outside ourselves
see that that further steps in evolution
if
if we're to have any relevance as a
hatching global organism
involves us participating in
interacting with that living context
outside ourselves
developing the capacities that enable us
to communicate with them
act first and foremost act
with one voice so you've probably heard
of the fermi paradox which is um
the fermi paradoxes well you know if all
this life is everywhere well
elsewhere in the universe why haven't we
seen it you know why don't we detect it
why
and and i would say the answer is is
that
um for the same reason that we don't
uh you know interfere in
embryos and try and talk to them and
deal with them and so on
uh we don't exist yet you know we're a
babble
we're subplanetary we we
uh yeah it's like i just have to share
this because it's
for me you know that calvin and hobbes
cartoons
yeah the little boy and the tiger um
there's a wonderful cartoon where they
they stand in front of a bunch of um
chopped off trees just tree trunks and
litter everywhere
and calvin says to hobbs i think the
most convincing
evidence for higher intelligence and
outer space is that they haven't
contacted us yet
yeah that's that's good that's good
but the but the key reason why they
don't you know so
so people say well you know won't they
help us over these difficulties
because they're systems thinkers
these other planetary organisms because
you don't get to their stage without
having
you know the success of at least some
systems thinkers to imbue the
the hatching super organism with systems
thinking if they're systems thinking
thinkers they know that the only way we
will develop
the global structures the constraints on
those global structures the consequence
capture for the whole planet
is if we go through these uh challenges
that evoke and call for
those emergencies so they would be
killing us to intervene
uh it'll be totally false concern
for us to take away these stimuli
and challenges that we need to develop
the structures that we
that that will help actualize us at the
next level
but coming back to the bad news i know
you're trying to distract me but the
um so coming coming back to the
embryo uh and the yolk
um and the
it hatching as a
uh as a chicken and as i said in
well you know we started on very small
scale and
diversified integrated progressively and
you know now we're covering the whole
shebang and we're on the verge of of
hatching
a global organism which is not just
humanity but humanity
and the whole living system the
the uh the chicken
leaves behind it you know the broken
eggshell
uh quite a bit of gunk
i'll just call it gunk but that was part
of the living
part of the egg because what what
quite a lot of the processes were in the
egg including the
shell itself was scaffold with
scaffolding
and scaffolding
you uh you believe behind that when you
hatch
you know um so all the living processes
on this planet uh you know when
humanity governs them
and that and implements consequence
capture it'll be
and and looks at how to you know make
the planetary organism into a viable
system that's as good a
good a model as you know most people
would have
staff would be this viable system um
when we do that then some of the living
processes and
parts of the ecosystems and so on uh
it'll become evident that they were
scaffolding
and we they won't come with us on our
journey
spin that analogy a bit further what
does that
mean in terms of
the complex ecosystems and planetary
well some yeah some but some of it
what proportion of it i have no idea but
some of it
won't be necessary for the flourishing
and might actually be
detrimental on a waste of resources for
the flourishing of the super organism
so
just was a little bit conscious of time
we've got about another
yeah in 15 minutes and and this kind of
edges onto something that also there's
two things and maybe we have another
call
um because it's been really insightful
for me and interesting
uh the the the two things that i kind of
wanted to ask you
in this context one is how
does like um
the whole pro social evolution
idea um square with with your take
but but this this might be for the next
call
um but the the role of technology in all
of this
um i have a sense that we
we were betting too much on technology
to to save us in in this because it's
it's actually part of that process that
takes us away from
understanding the um
[Music]
the dynamics at the lower levels of this
interconnected living system that we
need to keep
alive in order for our emerged
culture and intellect to actually
continue yeah
and well i suppose the second point
first
my my view is is that um
the there's no imperative to maintain at
all
in its pristine state like it was
forty thousand years ago um
that the the emergence of the chicken
makes a hell of a mess
of what was there before you know it
integrates it into
a new system a new coordinated
system and preservation for
preservation's sake
isn't part of that at all but just just
to be clear
when you when you speak of the chicken
you don't speak of humanity you speak of
of of a of a living whole thing yes
which which and let me just quickly
emphasize
um it won't be humanity
and it won't have humanity's values it
would be
just imagine if if the cells becoming
multicellular organisms
you know i sometimes imagine they had a
conference you know
and they said shit you know we don't
want to group together and
eating each other's shit you know you
know you know
all stuck to one another you yeah
they're like americans yeah
we want freedom we want freedom
basically to summon it up their values
as individual cells would be quite
inconsistent with the values
of the next stage you know of the well
unimaginable
to you know the so
the idea that somehow uh
you know the super organism will be a
manifestation of human values you know
is just
insane the
however the super organism will look at
look after humans at whatever level
they're at
and make use of them as part of its
system
but it'll try and develop humans
and one of the key steps in the
development of an
individual human being is to be able to
transcend their
the values and impulses they get from
their biological and cultural past
so it's the capacity to move at right
angles
to their biological and cultural past
and i don't know if it's happened to you
but
to pursue the path that i've both
pursued
then my original motivations which were
you know as a t
as a 20 year old you know large part of
self-aggrandizement and you know wanting
to
be a successful philosopher and be
revered and you know
nearly every scientist dreams have been
galileo or darwin
but you know that's i've had to
to to achieve the goals the evolutionary
goals yeah i've had to
you know and there's various techniques
you can do do it do for it but you know
i meditate and
and so on and i become try to become
transparent to my emotions and so on uh
in other words they flow through me i
note them but
they they're not me i don't i'm not
captured by them i'm not jerked around
by them i can move in any direction that
evolution demands of me
uh and that could be you know totally
different uh
human values uh we we won't get into
that now but
you know it might mean that i'm a
traitor i have to become a traitor to
australia
um to you know to advance the
evolutionary process
so whatever it demands of me i've
developed you know tried to develop the
capacity so so yeah the
the um so what green people
or orange people or blue people or
whatever value now
uh is highly unlikely to be
the values of this planetary organism
but there's it's important because you
know you made a in the use of spiral
dynamics you made a common
um you're probably not thinking of it
that way but the way you phrased it
and there aren't any green people there
aren't any blue people there aren't any
orange people it's it's
types in people rather than types of
people
yeah yeah just people that are arrested
in
their perspective in on that
particular value immune cluster um but
it doesn't mean that
once you're a green person you'll you'll
have to stay a green person you can you
can
actually make that's right and clearly
clearly the
uh consequence capture would operate in
the global super organism to
to organize processes that that maximize
the potential
development of of every human being
because
the uh you know they're the
highly intelligent potentially creative
components
that will enable the super organism to
be highly adaptive and highly available
um coming back to pro pro social
were you talking about was that an
allusion to david slain wilson's
yeah and right because it it seems
somewhat
related but but i i sense that it's not
the
same take at all
he speaks like that the summary is is
like
between individuals competitive
individuals will beat
collaborative individuals but between
groups collaborative groups will be
beat competitive groups sort of and
therefore
there's an evolutionary pressure towards
pro-social behavior
um it kind of links to some of what
you've been saying
but yeah he has no concept like
governance so he doesn't recognize
management as
as or anything like consequence capture
but no recently um over the last year
i tried to get the 15 top evolutionary
scientists in the world
to to say that evolutionary science now
can say something to humanity about
uh the evolutionary imperative
being that we move to a global society
with global governance and so on and and
i think
that whilst hardly any evolutionary
scientist has
you know said that directly except
davidson wilson in his latest book
did talk about a super organism it's a
small step
so they re most of my story except for
the data the pattern
so let's put it this way the pattern of
successive integration
is recognized by evolution science what
does it
you know what produces that pattern is
controversial
but for the point of view of saving
fucking the planet and humanity
um they can all sign up in my view to
the proposition that we need to go to
the next step as a global system global
coordination
so i tried to get davidson wilson to
lead it because i i don't have the um
you know the recognition and so on
delete it um
basically declined uh
the uh
it got a bit so and no one else put
their hand up
so now i'm i'll never give up i mean the
you know the the intentional move to a
global society is
you know the the goal of all
intentional conscious evolutionaries in
my view
um so i'm trying a different tech but
but um so david's pro-social
things which are all good you know all
one is his movement is evolution
institute and everything else
is all wonderful stuff but i did make
a sort of provocative comment in a in an
email to him where i basically said well
um you know yeah you're working at the
lower level and that's admirable
but the whole system's faced with
collapse and i said it's a bit like a
person whose
house is burning down and spends his
time
gardening and i say it's it's nice to
have a nice garden
around your house but if your house is
burning down
and you're focusing only on the
gardening then that's dysfunctional
so that was that was where we ended up
he didn't take too kindly to that ism no
no he didn't but um
still anyway yeah that must be your 15
minutes up
yeah unfortunately
because there's so many questions left
but in terms of leaving people with a
like coming briefly back to this this
technological question because
i can see how some people would listen
to this and then
immediately jump into a sort of um
[Music]
jack fresno venus project like
technologically
aided and let's get some sort of crypto
system
implemented that that just does the big
data thing and
and measures every resource use and and
positive contribution of every
human being in multiple
cryptocurrencies and for me all of that
is is some sort of
techno fantasy nightmare actually that i
wouldn't want to live in
because it is um also a restriction of
in the
individual freedom that maybe i'm not at
the point yet to
surrender that but what you were
speaking to was that
it doesn't necessarily mean that
everybody
understands um precisely
why these rules exist but
the rules enable everybody to flourish
and and and so that um
for me like there's a lot more to
explore here
particularly around this the link
between all of this
and subsidiarity that we can only build
a global
system of true participation of
everybody if we actually devolve
um part of the decision-making process
down to
the scale at which people have
consequence capture in their immediate
environments if we re
match our settles patterns of
settlements
in direct relationship to the health of
the ecosystems that we inhabit
then feedback is imminent is much faster
part of our problem is that we've been
building this global society that that
um
on not society but global system that
has
um meant that
so many of our actions in terms of
driving climate change
um have been buffered by the larger
system
and we spent 50 years
denying that we were running fast
against the wall
um so because yeah
because um you know our
current systems are perfectly organized
to result in the self-organization of
the destruction of human civilization
so consequence capture
consequent capture rewards and punishes
in relation to the
interest of the whole but our current
system rewards and punishes but what it
rewards is
behavior that kills other people
that uh destroys ecosystems that
you know is producing global warming so
you've got
so what what an activist is is um
is confronted with today is the exact
opposite of
the system the reward of bad behavior
the self-organization the system
self-organizes and rewards the bad
not the good so what chance have you got
so that that brings up in a whole
another area is because this yeah we can
have these ideas we
we can we can convince ourselves that we
know exactly where everything needs to
go
but how the hell do you get there um so
i've
i've a you know paper a companion to the
evolutionary manifesto was a
paper called strategies for advancing
evolution
and that's what it addresses and uh
and it takes into account the fact that
you know
all revolutionary movements which have
con
which basically uh you know experiments
for what we're talking about all
revolutionary movements have
have uh you know failed they've achieved
revolution
uh but then the old crap self-organized
self-organized again like russia and
and so on so how do you break out of
that dynamic you know that's that's
a fundamental issue that we haven't
touched on uh
and that's where i say i might have to
you know
um uh you know
be a traitor to australia somewhere
along the line because there might be
forces
well for me it is this this um and again
i might be stuck into
my own groove on my own record here but
but the the
i spent a lot of time working on
creating more
sustainable regenerative models at the
community scale
working with the ecovillage movement
yeah that small scale and at some point
realized that
from the sort of whole systems design
building synergy perspective
those scales were actually not big
enough to accommodate
certain ways of meeting human need needs
and that the regional scale made much
more sense
and was also much more aligned to the
larger part of our species history
um because the the sort of nation state
as i alluded to earlier
is really a relatively recent operation
and and of course that is um
kind of treasonous in some countries if
you if you say
um you know that's why david sloane
wilson i think
was not going to sign up to a you know a
move to global governance because in
america
yeah they'll shoot you for that i mean
it's worse than being a black man in
america
is you're more disadvantaged than if
you're an african-american
if you support global governance you
know everyone will be united against you
but
yeah yeah so for me yeah that
there's just something in um
learning from biological pattern that
is exactly that rather than dominate the
hierarchy's growth hierarchies
enabling hierarchies with some
coordination function which
which you would call consequence capture
that
that we need to re-build
into our settlement patterns in our
relationship with the wider
context and part of that to my mind is
also that letting go
of being so speciesist and understanding
that we have a key role to play that we
can be um
keystone species in the ecosystems that
we inhabit in
and do what life does best creating
conditions conducive to life
in those systems but that it that in
order to have the feedback
of our actions
inform us quickly enough where we're
going off track
it needs to be both scaled up
and scaled down at the same time it like
scale up our global awareness
and coordination and cooperation and we
actually need to redesign
the patterns of meeting our needs
at a much sub national level
a regional level by regional level two
two final points i'd make then
uh
i don't know that i was trying i'm
getting tired
um no so the general the technological
one uh because you've raised that a
number of times and
the so what i would say broadly is that
the one thing one certain thing about
complexity is you can't predict the
future
of everything impossible you know
complex systems are unpredictable
um like stuart kaufman for example says
there's no
pre-stateable uh
you know rules about how the future will
unfold
it's all unknown i don't go as far as
that i say there are
attractors you can identify attractors
so an attractor is the global
uh the you know the global super
organism the hatching
of what this whole process has been
headed towards the hatching of global
super organism
isn't a tractor so you can predict that
any planet that survives where
life survives and flourishes there will
be global governance and there will be
you know a global cooperative system but
the detail of how to get there is
unpredictable
so the most that has really important
consequences for the systems you set up
that you don't try and design the future
and you know in terms of mental models
predicting the detail the best you can
do is set up systems
that select uh and evolve
in the right directions so they
they work by um
there's no predetermined you know
ironclad plan there is instead
the setting up of complex systems which
develop and adapt
and evolve those plans so what that
means is to be more specific is
you can't a priority work out what the
role of technology will be
relative to the role of the ecosystem
um you don't know which parts of the
ecosystem are scaffolding that have
fulfilled their purpose and can be
dropped you can't do that any more than
you can say
you know that there will be some new
technology that we should focus on that
will solve all our problems
you have to but on that basis maybe
large parts of our technologies are the
extra
are the eggshell exactly
technology the fact that we can talk and
have this kind of level of conversation
across
basically spanning the globe literally
um
yeah i'd say 90 of of where technology's
gone
is what i refer to as simply the
masturbation of stone age desires
so it's satisfying human desires which
came
which were fixed at one point in our
evolutionary history
that served little purpose now uh and
the developing the using of oil the yolk
to produce you know all these structures
of buildings and
institutions and everything else to make
people happy
well you know humans being happy is
not the you know what won't necessarily
lead to the emergence of the super
organization
the hatching of the chicken you know so
just
i did remember the second point i was
going to mention and that is that um
oh how's it going hasn't gone again
uh damn it's gone again
technology um there was yeah there was
another one
nope it's gone the old age
we'll save it for the the the next next
time
um i will have another conversation
because this is really
rich um thank you so much
and um i don't think i've ever had a
conversation this long this was two
hours
and right like on on this series of um
of this this video blog that i'm doing
um but yeah thank you so much for
for your time and um let's let's let's
find find another
opportunity maybe towards the end of the
summer um because i'm trying to take a
little bit of time out and
focus on my family in my own life for
for a few
months well that's the principle of
subsidiarity so
you know looking after the lower levels
and making sure they're flourishing and
so on
so yeah i've really appreciated the
discussion as well because as my
daughters
point out to me you know i write about
cooperation but
but i haven't had many to escape well
hardly any discussions you would be
amazed
at how few truly stimulating discussions
i've had on these issues so
um so it's been fantastic for me and
definitely
um let's do it again okay
wonderful rest of the evening in
australia and i'll get on with my day
now here in
mallorca thank you so much good luck
with everything
thank you